[Music]
thank you
good evening and good day everybody good
to see you all today we are discussing
geopolitics and foreign policy and we
have with us the Learned Abhijit
is somebody who needs no introduction so
welcome Abhijit great to see you
can't hear you
I can't your mic is not connected
cannot hear you
it says your mic is not connected
I cannot hear you
no
okay let's wait for a few minutes for a
budget to reconnect I think he's gonna
try from his phone
thank you
in the meanwhile let's take a look at
who's there dungar Singh Chauhan zumuk
vikas Tejas silver Kapil
Jay devarshi arnab shail Sharma vallabh
harsh
rishikesh abhinav Aman
good to see you all people let's wait
for a couple of minutes for a widget to
reconnect
and then we will
get going with the discussion
So today we're going to talk about
Afghanistan we'll start with Afghanistan
everyone is interested in knowing what's
happening in Afghanistan today
so we shall start with that let's try
and understand what's happening
in Afghanistan
and then we will talk about some other
aspects of India's foreign policy
we will talk about India U.S
relationship we'll talk about the
india-pakistan relationship
the U.S China relationship and other
things as well
once Abhijit joins us
[Music]
let us see
I think he's joining back
hi Abhijit can you hear me
I can't hear you yes
okay yes I can hear you
great great I'm not at home which is why
I'm on my phone uh so it's not my usual
setup and all of that yeah
no problem it's working now so let's go
let's get going so let's talk about
Afghanistan first so that's the that's
what everyone's looking at right now
everyone's eyes are on Afghanistan so
the situation in Afghanistan it feels
like you're watching a once good TV
series in which all of the character
development all of the build up over the
past 10 15 Seasons it is completely
ruined by the writers in the final
season in the last two or three episodes
so what has actually happened did the
isi and Taliban actually defeat the us
or was this all or did the U.S achieve
everything they had actually ever wanted
what's exactly happened there
so it's several different things coming
to roost right uh the Assumption always
was that Afghan Army had been trained
well enough to hold its own certainly in
terms of equipment levels that we could
see on paper it was perfect
as long as you prevented a Pakistani
invasion
uh it was just fine
uh because you know they're good enough
to hold back the Taliban they're not
good enough to hold back the Pakistan
army with a full-fledged functioning
State and a professional military now
what's happened is you essentially have
a Pakistani Invasion happening uh they
are not supported by aircraft but they
are supported by all the uh electronic
intelligence the signals intelligence uh
uh ammunition equipment all of that uh
you know I tweeted a video out a week
back or something like that which will
show you that some of the Taliban were
actually wearing fatty kurtas the the
traditional dress but in patties and
things like that which you know the
Taliban never wears so there's something
happening out there all the intelligence
I'm getting from the ground not from the
Afghans because the Afghans tend to
exaggerate but from other people who
should know uh are also telling me that
it is you know commanded entirely by
seasoned old Pakistani military
commanders and things like that
so on one hand there's something like
it's not a Pakistani Invasion but it is
massive Pakistani assistance and uh
uh command uh and intelligence functions
either the pakistanis have provided
the same thing is that the Americans
they planned the withdrawal very badly
uh they had uh you know uh contracted
the only attack aircraft that the uh uh
Afghan government has is the Tucano you
know the uh Brazilian trainer aircraft
which they use for counterinsurgency
very effective aircraft uh uh but the
thing was they gave out the training to
a contractor who hadn't been paid in a
long time so the Afghan can't even get
the contractor to maintain the aircraft
because the Afghan Air Force wasn't
trained maintaining those aircraft and
things like that and you know out here
air power rules uh if you have air power
the enemy can't concentrate in numbers
you break down their numbers so clearly
airpar isn't working out here and
whatever strikes America has carried out
has been token strikes at best so that's
two
part number three is that the Afghans
themselves are at fault uh you know
they've been gobbling away money they
corrupt as hell uh a lot of these
battalions and Soldiers the ghost
battalions and ghost soldiers because
the generals would inflate numbers uh
claim that uh they had all these
soldiers and they needed money to pay
them
Corruption of the Afghan Elite is second
to nobody uh you look at ghani's own
nephew he's been posting images of him
flying his private jet quote and quote
from crisis to crisis it's a Gulf Stream
uh five or six five uh you know which
would set you back easily between uh you
know 65 to about 85 million depending on
the options uh you exercise
now where did that little took of a boy
get uh uh that much money nobody knows
but everybody you know understands who
is going out giving out that money uh uh
ghani is corrupt he's also incompetent
he won a rig the election uh uh you know
this was bound to happen because the
corruption everybody
now we also need to remember that you
know the last time there was a pull down
in things like that under Obama there
were significant reverses and then you
know confidence picked up you know we
can do with fewer American troops and
let's gain control again
the next thing we need to remember is
that you know when you say that all
these cities have fallen
aha
they went exactly in Afghan government
control because you know uh uh for me
the Taliban control started I I had to
go see the minerator of jam uh uh and uh
about 40 kilometers updated that was the
end of government control uh about 15 20
kilometers out of Kabul when you're
going to the panchil valley that's the
end of government control uh Marathi
Sharif on our way to bulk for example
died where rocks and the wife of
Alexander was born it was sacked by
Timur it was sacked by uh Genghis Khan
uh so when we went bulk uh the first few
to check ports outside uh uh mazari
Sharif where a government the next four
or five checkposts
so you know I'm sitting there thinking
uh even in terms of how close they're
coming in they're only advancing about
20 30 kilometers
right so it this notion that Afghan is
falling if you remember that piece I
wrote for chanakya Forum I detailed all
these things you know it's highly
doubtful you could have ever said it was
under government control because the
people hostile and the Taliban were all
over the bloody face
I don't know According to which idiot it
was ever under government rules because
then I went to Goran because it was
completely under palavan control and yet
I read the news about uh four or five
days back oh Gore has fallen Germany Has
Fallen
how
uh so understand the Taliban haven't
Advanced more than 20 to 30 kilometers
which itself is significant because the
government never really owned most of
the countryside the countryside was
always we went deep into samagan
Province uh you know helmond Province
and things like that it was deep deep
Taliban territory there was no
government out there
uh there was kind of a negotiated piece
in the sense the government would come
then the Taliban would come uh but you
always had to deal with Taliban going to
any of these rooted areas so so it's
four different things uh the American
cock-up the Pakistani role uh the
afghan's own complacency and Corruption
and then this mysterious perception that
people have that the Taliban where uh
very far away or things like that
so what was the U.S Exit Plan were they
aware that they were handing the country
back to the Taliban on a platter or was
this the deal all along in some way with
the isi
it's very hard to see uh uh you know
there's handland's razor right never
attribute to malice what you can do
incompetence uh so uh it's more likely
to be in competence the important thing
to remember is that the Americans are
still talking to the Pakistan where the
Americans carry out airstrikes they
still fly over Pakistani airspace not
Iranian space uh so there is that
communication on uh Yusuf uh the
Pakistani National Security advisor
who's a friend of mine incidentally uh
was in uh DC just a week back
uh so they are talking to the Pakistani
government
uh but there's been no official called
me to Imran Khan or anybody from uh the
party as
such so there's uh uh I don't know if
the Americans are trying to give the
impression
that uh they are boycotting the
government but in private they're
definitely talking to them a lot I don't
know why moid used to visit to
Washington didn't make news but I know
for a fact he was there uh uh just last
week
I see so now that the US has more or
less withdrawn from Afghanistan there
are three players left in the game which
is China Pakistan and Russia so what do
each one of these seek what does what
are their interests in Afghanistan we
know the Pakistani interest in
Afghanistan they seek this strategic
backyard but what about the Chinese and
what about the Russians what do they
seek
so herein lies the problem each one of
them has their agenda each one of them
is screwing the other over but each one
of the other things that the other is
not screwing them over right so uh uh
let me explain so for example the
pakistanis they want absolute control of
Afghanistan because they think
Afghanistan being the new age mineral uh
Paradise that it is could turn them into
Saudi Arabia so Pakistan wants to
control over a lot of Afghanistan's
mineral resources the initial thing why
this whole thing started which was you
know uh question iridism across the
border uh that uh is no longer the
driving Factor anymore it has a lot more
to do with mineral control and things
like that
and a sort of you know uh we won't know
how much they want it to be like a
Taliban Afghanistan just to launch
attacks on India and not take
responsibility for it
which will almost certainly be the case
but right now it seems to be at minerals
why because they realize the Chinese has
screwed them over they're in a serious
dead trap uh the Chinese aren't letting
them uh unlike the Americans who would
throw money at them every time they got
into trouble the Chinese don't uh you
know give the lunch to anybody
so uh they are now in the process of
trying to screw the Chinese over out
there the Chinese think they are going
to get the mineral rights at guck
and all those other places where the big
uh
information age uh deposits are uh
unfortunately it seems nobody in
Pakistan has told them that they're
going to keep it as unstable as possible
so China can't extract from there
uh the Russians is different the
Russians did this out of schaden Freud
to screw the Americans over the Chinese
also did it to screw the Americans over
incidentally that was one more uh
now the issue has always been if Russia
did it to screw the Americans over they
you chose the wrongest person possible
zamir Kabula president since uh
designated Afghan uh uh points persons
is a isi agent for all effects and
purposes
he's a nasty piece of work he claims to
be you know the be-all and end-all uh
but he is
people in the Kremlin will tell you that
he is a compromised piece of uh
this is the same man you know who's cut
India out of the uh Russian talks that
were held last week or something like
that this is the same man who said that
you know the route uh took peace in
Afghanistan lied through Kashmir
uh and the problem has always been we
never estimated how uh uh dangerous and
inimical to this interest this clown was
going to be not a clown uh he screwed us
over so he's definitely not a clown uh
this man was going to be and nobody ever
raised a good book nobody ever told them
you need to get rid of zamir khabulov or
we can't trust you
uh and so it turns out Russia has also
screwed us over indirectly because of
the nilka Buddha and zamil Kabula would
have been implicit in this because this
is their big hurray they would love
love nothing more than to see a uh you
know those uh images that came out
Vietnam you know the helicopter
evacuating it uh uh Embassy folk from
the uh roof of the embassy in uh Saigon
uh they want to see images like that
again which they've got I mean a Afghan
government polling is a huge foreign
policy crime for Russia
remember terror is uncontrollable the
Taliban might say we are going to
control Terror against uh we good Terror
against China they might say we are
going to control Chechen Terror against
Russia but you tell me Abhijit have you
ever found anybody who's been able to
control terrorists ever we tried you
know internally propping up zalescing
tried dropping up bindran Valley uh as a
counter to the akalis how did that end
for us they ended up killing the same uh
prime minister that he served uh Rajiv
Gandhi tried propping up the LGT against
the sinhadis and uh look how that ended
up for him so anybody who thinks that
they can control better
I mean you know there's only so many
times you can make this mistake you
can't keep making this mistake over and
over again
yes yes I agree totally so now that all
this has happened does India have any
role left in Afghanistan and does this
Taliban take over constitute a future
threat for India
it does it does because remember in 89
when the najibula government
[Music]
started losing ground when uh when the
Soviets withdrew well majipola held his
own to his credit uh he didn't collapse
as quickly as this government has
because there was a functioning of gun
State at that point of time uh what it
was that they held their own and all the
jihadis that had come to Afghanistan got
directed to kashmirs and that is the
beginning of the Kashmir resurgence
uh if you notice yesterday or day before
RPGs were found with kashmiri militants
now RPGs is a whole new level of
escalation for these ministers
they usually given guns or grenades and
things like that explosives yes not RPGs
RPG is uh you know it's a traceable
weapon you can trace its origin back so
it's almost a declaration of war like
Stingers or helicopters or things like
that right so so uh in this particular
case there's uh expect to see a lot more
RPGs coming into Kashmir I do see
a significant uh increase in terrorism
in the valley uh so that's one thing
that's going to affect us
quite badly uh our role to play well you
know we squandered role I think of all
we love talking to other people about
not uh
having wishful thinking and all that
crap ultimately turns out we're the
biggest Wishful thinkers are out because
you know this insistence happened on
democracy you should have known from day
one that the people in charge you didn't
need to have elections what you needed
was somebody nearly brutal and nasty or
uncompromising like say Abdul Rasheed or
amrullah Saleh or Abdullah in charge
even Abdullah Abdullah is a very kind
man so maybe even not him it should have
been somebody like dostam or amrullah
Khali in charge
uh we did we insisted on the Sham of a
democracy we insisted on uh weak sold
out people like uh ghani and Karzai of
course Karzai we didn't pick but ghani
we supported we support it uh so uh
we're paying the price for that there's
nothing we can do about it anymore uh
you know we should have one of the
things I noticed in 2019 when I was
there was house cyberized the Taliban
commanders bear because you remember the
last time the Taliban became too
powerful for Pakistan's own liking they
started taking independent decisions and
things like that which the pakistanis
never wanted
now uh they've learned their lesson and
they're keeping them siloized so they're
keeping them the way they have a sort of
jihad menageries
Etc et cetera Etc who they can provoke
later on to fight each other and kill
each other they're doing very much the
same thing out there uh local commanders
hate other local commanders they don't
talk to other commanders unless their
coerced because their families are being
held hostage in Pakistan or something
like that
they don't really listen to Pakistan uh
this was something we should have
utilized and the Americans told us to do
it the Americans made their own fair
share of mistake you know if you're
going to take a pre-industrial
uh sedentary pastoral Society that's
extremely violent that has resource
shortages and those resource strategies
means One Tribe attacks the other tribe
for women and livestock and grain every
uh two three years and kills and running
blood feuds in this country you wanted
to have a democracy with equal rights
for women and gay and lesbian rights and
like that you have to be on some
serious I mean this is beyond cocaine
this is beyond heroin this is some kind
of you know designer drug it's some
Crystal Method or something some super
Crystal Method of some kind that you
have been snorting but once the
Americans realize that mistake what did
he get
s on with this nonsense that we're not
doing there is no such thing as good
Taliban back
over and over because I was part of some
of those track twos where this was
discuss even about saying look we're
just saying good Taliban bad Taliban as
a rules the thing is they are followized
we need to stop saying divided rules
India went on saying no no no no no no
no
so we also screwed up out there very
very badly we should have started
because if Pakistan a stylizing dead you
use it to play divided rule what stops
you from playing divided rules so there
is that and then of course there's the
whole garbage Washington Think Tank
Brigade you know which went on making
apple uh apologies for Pakistan uh you
know uh you can't bomb Pakistan you
can't hold Pakistan to account so in
this entire process when is Pakistan
ever been held to account
zero and you know Pakistan is the root
of the problem so it was a bit like
going to the doctor with jaundice and
instead of him giving you something to
treat your liver he instead you know
recommends uh Chanel or yif salora
Foundation because your eyes and your
face are going so yellow he'll just say
Dad someone and cover up the yellow list
of skin
um so you know that compound mistakes
they have the role to play right now
exactly liquor wounds see what plays out
and then uh do what we need to remember
we did manage to have a friendly
Afghanistan the last 20 years
uh in spite of having a hostile
Afghanistan for two three years before
that under Taliban room uh the
mujahideen initially hated India because
we supported the Soviet Union but now
they all have their second homes in
Delhi
so uh it's uh let's wait and watch let's
wait and watch uh the one thing we can
always depend on
is Pakistan's stupidity and its ability
to overplay its hat so even if we lose
today don't lose hope
right so let's talk about India's
investments in Afghanistan so basically
you don't invest somewhere without
carefully evaluating and calculating the
return on investment so what was the
expected or hoped for return on
investment
I mean these Investments are supposed to
benefit the people of India and the
nation so where these Investments are
where they're merely gestures of
Goodwill
uh okay so first of all they went
investments in the commercial sense of
the world they were never meant to bring
any kind of profit to India uh they were
meant to bring people to the people of
Afghan
uh the local agricultural projects there
were dams and things like that
and the whole point of it was and this
is where India has been quite smart it
was meant to benefit the Afghan people
uh and reinforce the government
so in one aspect it failed in the
government reinforcement but in the
other in benefiting the Afghan people it
will it has it has succeeded
spectacularly it will continue to
succeed there are still people I've
spoken to several Taliban commanders who
have been touched personally their
families have been touched personally by
some Indian agricultural project or the
other
uh the Commander in Gore for example
opposite code or was it nothing I forget
uh his family farm gets water from an
Indian project he knows about it uh he's
always been grateful to India for it and
things like that and of course you know
we had a round where we were both uh
jointly spitting on Pakistan uh
this that whatever it was translated he
couldn't really speak too much he knew
his for some strange reason I don't know
how but he definitely knows uh
uh now the thing is what it gives you is
it gives you a very significant human in
can't hear you
okay let's wait for a couple of minutes
for Abhijit to return
very interesting story there okay he's
back
okay I'm not okay
I can hear you yes can you hear me yeah
okay good sorry uh I gotta call him
because I'm on my phone what it does is
it cuts
okay uh so what happened was uh you know
uh we will have a huge pool of Goodwill
in Afghanistan
except for Kandahar and maybe some
adjoining areas where experienced a lot
of hostility uh there's not a single
Afghan I've met who didn't like India
and hated Pakistan
so now the question is how do you
weaponize that how do you utilize that
how do you monetize it and make it
actionable
uh is he lost out on that and you know
this is what I've been seeing since 2019
since going there and talking to people
that you know stop going the problem
that our folks is they only read
American or British assessments and they
put their own layer of interpretation on
it there is no primary intelligence
connection
if they're bothered with primary
intelligence connection they would have
seen these cytos and our ability to play
divided rules with them they did not
even when the Americans and Brits tried
telling us there is this opportunity to
create divided rule I mean who would
know divide and Rule better than the
American Temperance right uh we still
did not
so it was a well of a Well Spring of
Goodwill that we squandered we did not
utilize
uh it's fine it's fine
uh uh now let's lick our wounds uh
everything's not lost uh you know you
can still use it to uh
create a
civil war situation out there I know
it's a horrible thing to say but uh
civil Afghanistan is no longer in our
interests uh now it must burn it must
continue to burn because uh pakistani's
troops need to be bombed down there the
last thing we need is peace so that uh
the fighters there the mujahid's there
get transferred to the Indian border uh
to start off something in Kashmir
so all the talibans still Pakistan's
creature or are they their own creature
I mean do they have a will of Their Own
uh they do have a will of their own
which is why they've been cyberized so
they have a very powerful vehicle the
question is uh you know Pakistan is
extremely good at dividing up the enemy
and then dealing with them peacefully
see we've seen this in Kashmir where he
never seem to learn our lessons and this
government is making the same
the same spot
you know we used to understand we used
to keep paying all these militant
leaders to come over and become
which is why you know every uh big
shopping mall Srinagar is owned by a
former militant
every former militant has some Posh
house in uh uh or what's that road
called I forget the Posh Road the Amrita
Mark of Srinagar I guess uh
I forget the name but uh
they have their house there but
uh what Pakistan has
is that it never hesitates to use both
carrots and sticks the Indian state will
not eliminate a militant leader once he
is surrendered and embraced back a Pax
indica
the pakistanis don't give a
ship when they feel they feel you are no
longer useful to them that's a very
powerful motivator you're an Indian
state that doesn't know how to use
sticks in a Pakistani state that knows
how to apply very few carrots but a huge
array of sticks
so and you know we sit down and pretend
that a lot of these leaders are still
legitimate we pretend we give them
political power and whatnot give their
meetings to the Prime Minister and what
who what have you
academies don't make that mistake they
do micromanagement very well
uh the problem with Pakistan of course
is they never see the map
so you know that's so good at
micromanagement but look at Pakistan
Pakistan is as much of a security
as Afghanistan is it's a Garrison State
with a Perpetual Siege and if they think
that this victory of theirs isn't going
to you know sort of Ricochet back on
them
uh they're happy because a lot of
pakistanis when you talk to them in
private
they see that they've kind of lost the
battle against terrorism that now it's
the tale that Wags the dog not the dog
wagging the tail
they're desperately trying to play a
rare guard happening and now they just
add it to their own problems in this
quest for strategic depth or whatever it
is uh kids still don't realize what's
the price they're going to have to pay
for it
so let's talk about the India U.S
relationship what is this relationship
right right now like right now in 21
because when you see U.S joint
statements with Pakistan they talk about
shared interests but with India it's all
about shared values so we know what
takes precedence it's always interests
our values so what is the Indian U.S
relationship like what's going on
uh look it's it's a decent ground it's
it's not going down the drain like a lot
of us thought that you know uh the kind
of uh loonies that had come into
government it was going to go down the
drain that hasn't happened if you look
at secretary uh Lincoln's visit it was
actually extremely well managed surprise
surprise uh uh he did not rub any uh he
uh in fact all the NGO types that are
going to meet him came back uh with
hemorrhoids because uh he hadn't really
listened to them at all uh he had
actually made India's case
for us at that particular meeting so
it's fine even things like say cats are
sanctions uh you know because their
ideas 400 missile systems from what I've
heard they've made a very convincing
case and uh
it's not really going to happen uh if it
happens there must be some last minute
lobbying by the Pakistan Lobby out there
for those sanctions to eventuate uh the
quad is going pretty damn well by our
estimate uh by the australianism it as
well so that's not going anywhere that's
the bigger game that they're not losing
fight off as long as they don't lose
sight of China
where on good ground
we're on good crops so it's
it's not as bad as some people would
like it out to be and in fact you know
talk of shared values why is that
happening
happening because you have a whole Cafe
but New York Times and things like that
saying we do not have shared values
which is why America needs to clamp down
a little
bit so every time they restate shared
values it's not so much about interest
over uh
values it's more about correcting the
narrative back home and refuting it
is the U.S a declining power now is it
in terminal Decline and is China's rise
Unstoppable I mean is it China's time
now
well no it is in China's time it was
uh you know this is
being a bit like uh
how should we put this uh
the Bronze Age collapse where it was
both the Hittites and
middle Dynasty Egypt sorry new New Egypt
collapsing and the Bronze Age people
taking over or a better more recent
example would be uh
uh you know how Rome and Persia were the
Paramount Falls and they fought each
other to a standstill and the Arabs came
and smashed both of them
so we're waiting for the Arab tribes to
come out of the desert and smash both
the old superpowers and that's it let's
thank you why uh in Beijing
what you see is their new controls on
businesses businesses have become
extremely unsafe they no longer feel
comfortable investing in China uh
because you know you never know when
you're going to get picked up and
started off to jail and given 11 year
sentence for spying the way the Canadian
was and things like that so that is
becoming a no-go's zone for uh a lot of
companies out there now remember the
theme is in the early manufacturing age
the state gains an unprecedented uh
pre-industrial States the state doesn't
have that much agency enforcement
deficits all of it it is
industrialization that enables you to
build a high state that could control
effectively control its bureaucracy and
the impostment
and when you enter the information page
because manufacturing is so disruptive
uh socially disruptive you need a strong
state to control all the centrifugal
forces uh then when you enter the
information age the state takes a
backseat and private corporations to
take the uh
Health now what you're seeing here is
two different trajectories they're both
industrialized both America and China
have industrialized the problem is China
isn't allowing the kind of industrial
Freedom required to take China into the
information age
uh where you know Alibaba has been
targeted uh Jack Ma has been targeted
lots of other companies
so this is going to be the end they
maybe reach about 13 14 000 per capita
but that it will get capped off out
there they are not going to go beyond
that anymore
uh so that is the uh capping of China
with America is different
it's that private companies have gained
so much power that it's gone back to the
feudal age where the state counts for
nothing and private companies are
running their own agenda
uh in this case the thought control
the comes from CRT through critical race
Theory and political correctness and
things like that which have essentially
terrorized
the U.S Workforce into no longer being
capable of the kind of innovation that
they once wear
so is America and because this entire
CRT mob has executed an Institutional
capture of the uh State powers of
America like you know all certification
now has to be CRT compliant and craft
like that
uh America is now in terminal decline
for a different but similar set of
reasons to China
you know we like I said we need to this
is the sapnid Empire versus the
Byzantine Empire we need to watch out
for the Arabs now
who the Arabs will be I don't know
that's the big question who are the
Arabs so does India have a better
alternative model to offer to the world
you know uh because our thing is we
never do a correct
Ways and Means study we have a very high
opinion of ourselves which is not shared
by anybody else
and you know these uh little throwaway
compliments that we get uh you know I
mean if somebody I mean look at my face
uh chubby bald squeaky voice uh uh you
know best like a a complete uh
hobo or slum dweller or whatever if
somebody comes and you know tells me or
Abhijit are the most handsome sexy man
I've ever met that's epitome of manhood
you're like Michelangelo's David and
this and that I'll be like
yeah right I mean you know I've got my
reality check in place
Indians aren't like that
Indians are like they look and talk like
Abhijit Mitra and they believe people
when people come and tell Abhijit Mitra
that you look like you're the you're the
closest to Perfection to human
Perfection of male beauty that has ever
happened since Michelangelo did
they will actually believe that
uh you look at Indian policies so unit
of negotiation policy that uh focused on
problem solving over learn by Road
your problem is one of scale
in a scale project you have to sort it
out through learn by Road you can't do
problem solving problem solving is
highly subjective it doesn't work on
that kind of scale
and yet they've gone with that policy
which reminds you nobody in the
commentary actually called out they
called out the uh you know subject
matter of the syllabuses and things like
that but nobody actually questioned the
fact not the congress not the not the
right
the fact that how you find the problem
solving teacher Force you know all your
teachers have been brought up and
learned by wrote how are you going to
train them you're not training up a
teacher to even teach problem solving it
requires a huge capital investment in
teachers
how are you going to do that see that we
have all these and how you're going to
get to see our trillion dollars economy
with such a poorly trained Workforce
so nobody actually does the ways and
means study in India we love cutting and
pasting and invariably we cut and paste
all the wrong answers you know it's like
if somebody asks you
in the uh a leaked exam sheet that you
got
uh uh the uh
a question number eight was what is two
plus two
uh but in the action paper somebody
switched the sequence and they asked you
what's four plus four you still didn't
cut it and pasted the answer for what is
two plus two on there that's what we
tend to do we're very bad at cutting and
pasting you're a China industry is kind
of like that they they understand the
how when they steal technology they
don't understand or why so as long as
you don't understand the first
principles you can't really do too much
damage
in India the cut and paste policies are
very similar it's kind of CopyCat of
what the West does without
understanding what a context is we ask
the wrong questions we answer the wrong
questions and very frequently we choose
the worst examples
so what's the cause of this why do we
produce
such is is it a question of leadership
what needs to change
it's a question of leadership the
question of the kind of policy inputs
that the leadership gets you know if you
got a generalist bureaucracy that has
been trained in learn by Road
that have no specialization that have
never had a specialization in their life
they've come out of college they've
never had any work experience they get
straight into the bureaucracy and that's
it they're set for life and they are
expected to manage an extremely complex
industrial and economic environment that
even seen and experts don't know how to
manage uh you know you it's asking for a
bit too much now the thing is a smart
person should know their own limitations
and they should know uh what I call a
you don't need to know everything but
you need to know who is bullshitting you
and who's not
uh are political executive doesn't have
a meter and our unelected
executive
uh are essentially a sort of uh Guinness
World Record pile of bush
so between not having a meter
and an excess supply of uh you
will end up plus
equals
yeah unfortunately unfortunately yeah so
let's go back to geopolitics uh as
America declines
what does the future hold for Israel
so Israel Is On Solid ground right now
because they got rid of Netanyahu who
was the biggest thorn in the Democrat
side so as long as it's I mean Bennett
and yeah lucky then people like that
they're happy with it uh Bennigan's uh
they're happy with that so that
relationship is fine the Thorne who was
Netanyahu has been removed uh the
problem is I don't think naphthali
Bennett understands economics as well as
you know Netanyahu essenti is the man
almost single-handedly responsible for
taking Israel from a middle power uh
middle-income country to a high income
country to a very high income country
Natalie has a lot of good qualities but
that fundamentally crony capitalism that
and chronic capitalism can be a very
good fit you know as uh South Korea or
Taiwan Japan uh or Israel will show you
uh it's a it tries uh you you can
actually make a country very rich on the
basis of cruel cancer
uh we don't that's a different matter
but they have
uh
but anyway Thorn is gone so it's all
good on that score
the big question is how will bidens
approach an Iran affect this whole thing
but I can tell you the Iranian the
Israelis the Saudis and the uh amiratis
they are coordinating diplomatically
very very very carefully Alicia
so the Saudis are just throwing money
where it counts the amiratis are playing
their own brand of Charmed around the
Sea World Cups and the Israelis are just
doing uh
what they normally do which is bringing
huge amount of political heft to pay and
coercion and where necessary you know uh
secret porn tapes whatever it is that
the most sub deliverables for them to uh
manipulate things
so what's the deal with Iran right now I
mean Iran is under sanctions but with
this new Chinese deal that they have
will they do well with that I mean what
is the long-term uh game plan there I
mean what is Iran's geopolitical
Ambitions would a nuclear armed Iran be
good for the neighborhood
it definitely would be good for the
neighborhood uh
cities there's an argument that if Iran
goes nuclear then it's need to support
that fundamental insecurity why it
supports terrorism across
uh uh the region will go away that's not
the way things work uh what happens with
Pakistan once Pakistan got UK weapons
did it uh Instinct for terrorism go away
no because it's like a managing tiger
that's tasted blood
right so terrorism will continue but it
will continue Under The Shield of uh uh
nuclear umbrella which is never good for
the region because then you really can't
take action against Iran number one
number two uh
Ray C the new president will drive a
very hard deal I don't know why they
chose raisy but ricey is kind of the
worst person they should they would have
chosen to make a deal and I think they
chose it deliberately chose a hardliner
because their negotiating position now
is going to be hey we lived up to the
jcpoa they got nuclear team we just call
it the Irani creative the jcpo is
technical mumbo jumbo uh uh and you did
not the Americans unilaterally withdrew
you owe us compensation for the four
years we lost so you're going to
pay us back with interest
and there's nobody better than right AC
to pull off that act so now they're
going to get a arm and a year from the
uh
and I'm in a leg from The Americans
is Biden in the position to do that I
don't know but I can tell you the uh so
these amiratis and the Israelis they're
all storing up their bullets for that
particular fight when Biden actually
goes into uh back into the Iran utility
again
and what about the china-iran nuclear
deal what does that mode for uh
Iran a China nuclear deal isn't going to
go anywhere because if they do it is
going to get sanctioned immediately but
China will not want number one number
two
the Iranians know the Chinese very well
have you ever seen any major projects
unlike Pakistan who is dumb who get into
problematic situations they don't know
how to get out of
uh have you tell me where have you seen
the Iranians ever get into a tight
Embrace with the child
where if they ever opened up their
jugular
even during the last round of sanctions
before the Iranian creating did you see
them get cozy with the Chinese no they
understand the Chinese extremely well
they are not going to hand over the
nuclear jugular to the Chinese and let
the Chinese set up nuclear power plants
because they also have experience with
Chinese nuclear power plants like for
example
the Chinese nuclear power plants in
Pakistan most of them don't actually
even work properly the ones that are
meant for nuclear weapons do work but
the rest don't really
stand up to anything
so the Iranians know in private when you
talk to them they know what
uh the Chinese bring to the table
talking about India now the ACT East
policy that we have that we have or had
I don't know if it is still there what
happened to it I mean did we have any
concrete objectives in the military
economics or geopolitical objectives
what actions have been taken and what
happened to it
um so you remember the uh Luke East
policy when it was called Luke East was
started off because India wanted to
reorient the entire uh
uh uh
Outlook
uh from being very Occidental Centric to
being an oriental Centric thing and it
was initiated when there was a a huge
amount of growth happening in India
since then our growth has been less than
spectacular it's not uh nobody's really
talking about the India growth story
anymore or the great potential for
growth in India and things like that
so that stalled quite a bit
militarily again we haven't really uh
integrated with Southeast Asian military
the way we should have diplomatically
this still pretty clueless you know we
still kind of Outsource our asean policy
to Singapore Singapore for all effects
and purpose
so uh
you know you could change it to act East
policy but again this is like uh these
are slogans which this government is
very good at unique in India which then
fails completely and you change it to
Atman is without actually changing
anything uh with the same clown in uh
charge uh so nothing's gonna happen
Amitabh can't
you have a five trillion dollar economy
without looking at the basic
fundamentals of how you're going to get
there so again nothing's going to happen
to this because this change of
nomenclature from look East to act East
it only works and it works very well if
your economy is moving
if your economy is not booming
forget about it at nine to ten percent
growth you'll be doing very very well at
six to seven percent growth
even uh
even up to eight percent growth you're
not really going to get the kind of
traction you need uh especially not in
most your FDI is coming from Mauritius
because everybody knows what kind of
money comes into Malaysia
and talking about the economy the past
two years we've had no growth whatsoever
so is is the has the policy been good of
locking down the entire country for a
year and a half I mean does it make any
sense to you
see this is one of those things where
you know it's very easy to be unfair to
the government the question was how many
people are going to die or the
opportunity cost where how many people
are going to die because of the economy
so it was uh who who what is going to
kill more people covet or the shutting
down of the economy right so there's no
right answers to it in retrospect could
it have been better managed yes uh but
did it have to happen it's very easy to
say no now with the benefit of hindsight
but at that point of time it probably
did have to happen so you know we can't
have a retrospective with the government
for something that uh was extremely
extremely scary
number one uh number two uh we've had
growth I mean we've had growth but it's
the lackluster growth so back to the
Hindu date of growth in that sense
uh don't go by player in the next year
because you know when you decline
rapidly then and when growth comes back
to normal it seems like you've picked up
to the same level which you have not uh
so uh ignore that the the real test of
what happens with our economy starts in
2023 24 and places like that
right no about diplomacy India's
diplomacy and engagement with the world
I mean
okay no problem no problem okay last
question and let's go
what do you think of India's tiny
diplomatic core I mean does India need
to increase its diplomatic core in order
to engage with the world properly
right so it's not just increase the
Diplomatic core why do we need to
increase the Diplomatic code so that
they actually gain primary intelligence
uh you know this uh you you need to
increase the Diplomatic uh course
numbers you need to retrain them
properly because right now they do not
gather information they don't archive
information and they don't hand it over
do you know how many times I've had to
make introductions in DC or Moscow for
certain people because the previous
person who helped the post did hand over
all their contacts and things like
or their accumulated knowledge it tends
to be so heavily personalized uh uh you
can have complete flip-flops policy
overnight or flip-flops of Engagement
overnight and it's very very problematic
so uh you know there's a certain
discipline required uh there's a certain
uh uh you know regard to primary uh
uh research within that uh uh this thing
that's required there is a need to
standardize policies uh standardized
ambassadorial temperament and training
uh and priorities and set and this is
what policy planning was meant to do but
it never did ultimately
uh there's a lot of things you have to
do there is a huge amount of internal
reforms that needs to happen in addition
to increasing the numbers numbers by
themselves aren't going to solve the
problem because you know like uh Gamal
Abdullah used to see 50 zeros still
makes a zero
um Siri you can you've got 700 uh zeros
right now uh if you increase it to three
thousand zeros you're still going to get
a zero you need to make them five or six
or seven in which case they can have are
very effective and mind you the numbers
actually came down under the Congress
comments for some 720 730 people now
we're down to 690 people so they're
actually smaller than the Singapore
diplomatic core
that's amazing
all right thank you so much thank you
for your time really enjoyed the
discussion and uh look forward to seeing
you later
thank you so much
sorry for all the uh interruptions and
all of that because I'm away from home
so uh great chatting with you buddy
pleasure was all mine take care
thank you bye